<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Gastón Palomeque</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Gastón Palomeque</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ggp1.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Mastering SQL with Go - Part 2</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/mastering_sql_with_go_p2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/mastering_sql_with_go_p2/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the part 2 of a series covering &lt;strong>sql&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Go&lt;/strong>, this time, we will cover how to work with SQL transactions context and isolation levels, results dynamic scanning, full text search and recursive queries as well as using multiple result sets to do many queries in a single roundtrip.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>To go to part one, click &lt;a href="../mastering_sql_with_go_p1">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="transactions">Transactions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s start with transactions, why are they necessary?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A transaction is a way for an application to group several reads and writes together into a logical unit.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mastering SQL with Go - Part 1</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/mastering_sql_with_go_p1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/mastering_sql_with_go_p1/</guid><description>&lt;p>I found myself using SQL a lot in one of my projects and I have learnt many things while trying to solve the problems I encountered.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This post is the part one of a series where I will try to show how to manage data in a relational database using SQL (Postgre syntax), Go and its standard library package &lt;a href="https://github.com/golang/go/tree/master/src/database/sql">&lt;code>database/sql&lt;/code>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Explaining absolutely everything would require an entire book so I will skip the subjects that most articles already cover (connection establishment, foreign keys, parameterized arguments, etc).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Applications containerization</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/applications_containerization/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/applications_containerization/</guid><description>&lt;p>The concept of containerization was first introduced in 1979 during the development of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chroot">chroot&lt;/a> (Version 7 Unix), which restricted an application&amp;rsquo;s file access to a specific directory - the root - and its children.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The main benefit chroot brought in was &lt;strong>process isolation&lt;/strong>, improving the system security such that an internal vulnerability wouldn&amp;rsquo;t affect external systems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In fact, chroot was the first of a series of technologies designed to protect each process from the others on the operating system.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Jubilación: estafa convalidada</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/jubilacion_estafa_convalidada/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/jubilacion_estafa_convalidada/</guid><description>&lt;p>• Las personas están OBLIGADAS a RESIGNAR el 11% del sueldo, 1.32 sueldos por año
• Se le quita al individuo la libertad de destinar ese capital a lo que considere más oportuno, inclusive generando beneficios muy superiores a lo que recibe una vez deje de trabajar (interés compuesto)
• Las personas pagan algo que no saben si van a recibir o en qué cuantía: la persona puede mudarse, fallecer, la economía puede colapsar, el poder adquisitivo del dinero del país puede deteriorarse, los gobiernos de turno pueden
• Hay personas que perciben la jubilación sin tener, los mal llamados, aportes.
• Hacer cálculo del interés compuesto de una persona asumiendo que su sueldo es de 600 USD y crece al mismo ritmo que la inflación (poder adquisitivo pseudo-constante), que invierte el 11% de su sueldo (66 USD) en el S&amp;amp;P 500 (~9% retorno promedio) por mes y trabaja desde los 25 a los 65 años.
El resultado es: 421,296.12 USD, simplificando muchas variables y tomando la inflación promedio del dólar de los últimos 45 años serían 144,600 USD del presente. Si tomamos en cuenta que la persona a los 65 saca este capital del mercado progresivamente, podría dividirlo en 480 meses y así tener 301 USD por mes (a poder adquisitivo de hoy, obviando los intereses ganados durante esos 20 años para simplificar la cuenta).
Estamos asumiendo muchas cosas pero aún pifiando feo en los cálculos la jubilación sigue dando &amp;ldquo;retornos&amp;rdquo; minúsculos y ridículos. Cabe aclarar de ninguna manera la jubilación es una inversión, sino un sistema diseñado para que los políticos de turno se llenen más los bolsillos con la excusa de &amp;ldquo;proteger tu capacidad financiera&amp;rdquo; en un futuro.
Agregar imagen del gráfico de barras. &lt;a href="https://www.omnicalculator.com/finance/compound-interest">https://www.omnicalculator.com/finance/compound-interest&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Stop protesting, start acting</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/protests_inefficiency/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/protests_inefficiency/</guid><description>&lt;p>A lo largo y ancho del planeta, miles de personas se agrupan en lugares públicos para protestar en busca de un cambio, que en la apabullante mayoría de las ocasiones, nunca llega.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="contra-organismos-privados">Contra organismos privados&lt;/h3>
&lt;h3 id="contra-organismos-públicos">Contra organismos públicos&lt;/h3></description></item><item><title>Protect your information</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/protect_your_information/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/protect_your_information/</guid><description>&lt;p>Every day we are more connected with our devices, we use them to share information, store capital, buy products, work, learn, for entertainment; basically anything.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Along with these services come our accounts, that hold and will hold more value than ever as the time goes by.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s no doubt we need them safe. In this article, I will try to help you &lt;strong>protect your information&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="passwords">Passwords&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Passwords are the &lt;strong>most critical part of every system security&lt;/strong>, they are the key that protect very sensitive information so it&amp;rsquo;s specially important to understand how to manage them carefully.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>React Native generic list</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/rn_generic_list/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/rn_generic_list/</guid><description>&lt;p>React Native&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>FlatList&lt;/em> is a component that supports many cool features while being simple and easy to use, it&amp;rsquo;s a good example of a well-designed piece of software and that&amp;rsquo;s why I decided to take it a step further.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For that, I&amp;rsquo;ve developed a generic list built on top of it that handles &lt;strong>pagination&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>refreshing&lt;/strong> internally, reducing a &lt;em>lot&lt;/em> of repetitive code from my previous implementation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I looked for something like this online but couldn&amp;rsquo;t find anything similar, even though it might be useful for many people, so I decided to share it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Security</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/security/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/security/</guid><description>&lt;p>Security is information, probability and incentives&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cryptography 101</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/cryptography_101/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/cryptography_101/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The new monetary standard</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/new_monetary_standard/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/new_monetary_standard/</guid><description>&lt;p>The stability of modern monetary systems depends on people&amp;rsquo;s trust on the governments and institutions that rule them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Central banks impose the currencies used and arbitrarily control money supply and interest rates. Their negligent manipulation have caused inflation and hiperinflation crises all over the world, driving people to look for better ways of storing their capital to protect it from money debasement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The search for a solution along with the advances in computer science and cryptography led to the creation of a decentralized virtual system that does not require to trust on a third party to exchange assets in a secure, transparent and reliable manner. This system is called &lt;strong>Bitcoin&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Rich Content</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/sample/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 19:53:33 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/sample/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hugo ships with several &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/content-management/shortcodes/#embedded">Embedded Shortcodes&lt;/a> for rich content, along with a &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/about/privacy/#configuration">Privacy Config&lt;/a> and a set of Simple Shortcodes that enable static and no-JS versions of various social media embeds.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="x-simple-shortcode">X Simple Shortcode&lt;/h2>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>{{&amp;lt; x user=&amp;#34;GoHugoIO&amp;#34; id=&amp;#34;1315233626070503424&amp;#34; &amp;gt;}}
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;br>
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">Profile is a customizable single-page portfolio theme for Hugo featuring a contact form and blog. Made by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gurusabarishh?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@gurusabarishh&lt;/a>.&lt;a href="https://t.co/KwYcwfdy16">https://t.co/KwYcwfdy16&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; GoHugo.io (@GoHugoIO) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/GoHugoIO/status/1315233626070503424?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">October 11, 2020&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>


&lt;br>
&lt;h2 id="vimeo-simple-shortcode">Vimeo Simple Shortcode&lt;/h2>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>{{&amp;lt; vimeo 146022717 &amp;gt;}}
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;br>

&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
 &lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/146022717" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="vimeo video" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>

&lt;br>
&lt;h2 id="youtube-simple-shortcode">Youtube Simple Shortcode&lt;/h2>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>{{&amp;lt; youtube w7Ft2ymGmfc &amp;gt;}}
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;br>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
 &lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/w7Ft2ymGmfc?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video">&lt;/iframe>
 &lt;/div>

&lt;br>
&lt;h2 id="theme-custom-shortcodes">Theme Custom Shortcodes&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>These shortcodes are not Hugo built-ins, but are provided by the theme.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hacking techniques</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/hacking_techniques/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/hacking_techniques/</guid><description>&lt;p>Our information isn&amp;rsquo;t and will never be &lt;strong>100% safe&lt;/strong>, for those that are interesed in learning more about cybersecurity and hacking techniques, here are some of them.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="unencrypted-services">Unencrypted services&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s clear that most people prioritize functionality and usability over security and privacy, they aren&amp;rsquo;t forced to use services lacking this last two principles but it&amp;rsquo;s still necessary to show them what really happens behind the scenes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until 2016 that Whatsapp implemented end-to-end encryption (basically anyone intercepting your&amp;rsquo;s smartphone traffic was able to read your conversations), or Zoom, whose calls were super unencrypted during the most of the 2020 and people still kept using them; Discord is another one offering unencrypted services.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Los pilares de una sociedad</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/los_pilares_de_una_sociedad/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/los_pilares_de_una_sociedad/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="descentralización">Descentralización&lt;/h2>
&lt;h2 id="propiedad-privada">Propiedad privada&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Si se me pusiera la tarea de, basado en un único índice, determinar la calidad de vida en una sociedad, ese sería el respeto por la propiedad privada.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="individualismo">Individualismo&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>La persecución de nuestros propios intereses nos conduce natural o, mejor dicho, &lt;strong>necesariamente&lt;/strong> a preferir la inversión más beneficiosa para la sociedad.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Las personas que esperan su felicidad de mano de sus gobiernos o de un “colectivo”, esperan una cosa que es &lt;strong>contraria a la naturaleza humana&lt;/strong>. Cada hombre tiene el cargo providencial de su propio bienestar y progreso porque nadie puede amar el engrandecimiento de otro como el suyo propio; no hay medio más poderoso y eficaz de hacer la grandeza de una sociedad, que dejar en cada uno de los individuos el cuidado y poder pleno de trabajar su personal engrandecimiento.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Comments</title><link>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/comments/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ggp1.github.io/posts/comments/</guid><description>&lt;p>Update Cryptoeconomics post to Bitcoinomics, remove proof of stake and focus on explaining Bitcoin, replace blockchain use cases with Bitcoin blockchain use case. In summary, refactor post&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Los monopolios sin imposición son beneficiosos para la sociedad.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For many things that seem to be true when we concentrate on a single economic group are seen to be illusions when the interest of everyone are considered.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Un conjunto de regulados odia al regulador, a menos que sean socios.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>